[Music]
the spice fenugreek is considered to be
one of humanity's oldest medicinal
plants
what can it do
in my last video on fenugreek i explored
the evidence showing it can improve
sexual function in both men and women
decrease menstrual pain and boost milk
production in lactating mothers
and what are the side effects
15 randomized controlled trials show on
average a significant improvement in
cholesterol levels and a dozen other
studies show significant improvements in
both long and short-term blood sugar
control in diabetics and pre-diabetics
using an average of about a half
teaspoon a day over a period of an
average of two months
results clearly indicate that fenugreek
is an inexpensive low-risk dietary
supplement that has potential to improve
blood sugar control and diabetes
what exactly is the mechanism by which
it lowers blood sugars there's a
peculiar amino acid in fenugreek that
increases insulin release from the
pancreas the peculiar 4 hydroxy
isoleucine has been described as an
efficient compound in the regulation of
insulin secretion
due to the fact that acts as a secretog
in the presence of elevated blood
glucose concentrations
has been proposed for the potential
treatment of insulin resistance diabetes
and obesity
now there's a class of diabetes drugs
that does the same thing sulfonyureas
soldiers like glucotrol gliburide
micronase glipozide the problem is that
they increase insulin secretion whether
you need it or not and so there's a risk
of severe hypoglycemia
driving your blood sugars too low
the funky fenugreek amino acid on the
other hand only boosts it when you need
it when your blood sugars are normal it
has no effect it only seems to stimulate
extra insulin release when you need it
most when your blood sugars are high
what these researchers did it was after
consent was obtained from family members
pancreases were obtained from brain dead
organ donors
put the insulin secreting cells in a
petri dish at a low blood sugar
concentration and they release a little
insulin and at high blood sugar levels
they release more insulin that makes
sense that's what they're supposed to do
since insulin is the hormone your body
releases when trying to bring down your
blood sugars
add in some of that fenugreek amino acid
though and you can boost insulin
production great but if that happened
even at the low blood sugar
concentration too it would be like the
drugs and you could dip too low but no
when you don't need extra insulin no
fenugreek effect
what about the role of fenugreek in the
prevention of type 2 diabetes a
three-year randomized controlled study
of the efficacy of fenugreek on men and
women diagnosed with pre-diabetes
those randomized to fenugreek were told
to take 1 3 teaspoons of fenugreek
powder twice a day before meals and both
the fenugreek and control groups that
didn't get any fenugreek were both given
identical diet and lifestyle advice and
by the end of the study the cumulative
incidence rate of diabetes was reduced
significantly in the fenugreek group
check it out
those who didn't get the fenugreek had a
four times higher chance of developing
diabetes and you could already see the
group starting to diverge within six
months and all from just a few cents
worth of a spice
every day
if you yourself want to intimately
support this kind of amazing research in
the future
be sure to register at organdonor.gov
[Music]
you